(speaking in foreign language)
- Good morning, everyone.
All right, so I wanna say hi to all of you
because we're gonna return to this series
of our 10th anniversary called Next.
(speaking in foreign language)
And you have to picture the Bible as a grand story,
is a grand story from the first book to the last book
from Genesis to Revelation.
It talks about God who sends himself actually to the world,
to this broken world to redeem us.
(speaking in foreign language)
So kind of the first episode is that God calling Abraham
and through this man, through him and his family,
God promised to bless as many people as possible,
as many people as sand on the seashore.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then there was Exodus
because they were in Egypt for a while
and then God saved them from Egypt, so Exodus,
and then in the tabernacle, in the wilderness,
God is with them in the tabernacle
and we learn about the faithfulness of God.
(speaking in foreign language)
So here's a quiz for you, okay?
So look at the map on the right.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, you trace the red line for me.
Okay, where do we start?
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, so the red map, I mean, the map on the right,
is I made the map.
(speaking in foreign language)
So it traces the Exodus story all the way to Joshua
when they crossed the river.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then there's one thing you need to notice
in this journey, it's not a straight line.
(speaking in foreign language)
God did not lead his people in a shortcut role
because they will lose their heart
and they will turn back to Egypt.
And because the people are stubborn and rebellious,
the trip, you know, it would have taken weeks,
but now it takes 40 years.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now if you trace this map from the left,
did you see Rameses?
(speaking in foreign language)
All right, all right, pretty good, pretty good.
You're a good student.
And then you see the Bala Lake, which is the Red Sea.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, and then down there in the triangle thing,
the peninsula is called Sinai Peninsula.
You see Mount Sinai.
(speaking in foreign language)
So they went, you know, from left to right
and they go down.
(speaking in foreign language)
And they go all the way go up there.
You see the circle there?
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, that's when they sent the 12 spies
to spy out the land of Canaan.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then, of course, they were unfaithful.
And then they wander in the wilderness,
detour for 40 years, and then around,
finally around, after 40 years,
around the Transjordan on the right,
and then all the way come to, finally,
they are at the edge of the bank of Jordan River.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, so you see the road is winding and puzzling.
And then 40 years of road, and then it's,
you think about it, it's a picture of our own lives.
(speaking in foreign language)
Think about your path, think about where you've been,
where you lived before.
It's rather, it's rarely a straight line.
(speaking in foreign language)
And there are detours, there are passes,
there are season that you feel like you are going backward,
and then the road is kind of winding all the time,
and sometimes you feel lost,
and you feel like God is not carrying you through.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then you have to remember, God is faithful to you.
So this same God who brought Israel
to the edge of River Jordan has carried each one of us
to the place where we stand today.
(speaking in foreign language)
That's why when Moses revealed the 40 years
with the people of God before they crossed Jordan,
he says, Deuteronomy 2 and 1 here,
these 40 years, the Lord your God has been with you.
You have lacked nothing.
And then the Lord your God carry you
as a man carries his son all the way you went.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then finally, we come to the bank of River Jordan.
And we come to the book of Joshua, chapter three and four.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, the crossing over is actually a key word
in the book of Joshua,
because this is the story, the history
that God is bringing his people across the river,
crossing the river into the promised land,
into the inheritance.
(speaking in foreign language)
So as you can see on the PowerPoint,
Joshua three and four,
these two chapters are actually pretty simple
from step one to three and four.
(speaking in foreign language)
So first is to prepare.
The people of God have to consecrate themselves
for tomorrow, God will do wonders among you.
And they have to follow the Ark of the Covenant
at a distance for you have not crossed this way before.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then God says some promises to them
and promised them the living God is among you
and the Ark of the Covenant will pass over before you.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then the third part is crossing the river itself.
So the priests have to step into the water
and then the water is cut off so that people can cross.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then today, when you go to Israel,
you find the Jordan River is very small.
It's just like a canal.
(speaking in foreign language)
It's because the upper river,
the modern nations, Israel and Jordan
have built a lot of modern dams
and that's why the amount of water is reduced
to flow into the river.
(speaking in foreign language)
But look at the picture on the right,
which is the black and white picture.
It was taken before all these modern dams were built.
It was taken in the early 20th century
when the river Jordan was flooded,
the river can stretch like half a mile wide.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, that is the situation when the people of God
at the bank of river Jordan, when the river was flooded.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, my question for you,
do you think the ancient people can swim?
(speaking in foreign language)
Do you swim?
Anyone swim really well?
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, wow, wow.
Paul, you can swim really well.
Can you swim like half a mile?
(speaking in foreign language)
Oh, okay.
I thought, I thought.
No?
No worry?
Maybe he's really good.
But, you know, if we cross the river Jordan by swimming,
then he's the only guy who can cross it, right?
(speaking in foreign language)
And then we will all be drowned in the flood water.
And then, you know, if you go to London,
go to the British Museum,
you'll find there's some fantastic Assyrian war relief.
And you see Assyrian soldiers can cross the river
by swimming.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then what we see here is the soldier
is carrying some sort of float, you know,
made by goat skin.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then they inflate it,
and then they can, you know, kind of huck it, right?
Hold it as a float,
and then they can swim across the river.
(speaking in foreign language)
That's very interesting, right?
So you have a purse, or you have a leather LV bag,
you know, don't throw it away, okay?
You know, you can inflate it,
and then, you know, kind of have like a float,
and then you can, you know, in case we drown, you know,
in case you drown, you can carry it,
and then swim across the river.
(speaking in foreign language)
But, you know, you need to understand
the ancient Israel people,
they did not have those technology.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then now the story says in 315,
now the River Jordan overflows all its banks
throughout the time of harvest.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now throughout the years, this is the hardest
and the most dangerous time to cross the river.
And it's interesting, God did not wait for a dry season
for the people to cross the river.
He chose the flood season, late spring,
so that when they cross the river,
it proves that this is the work of God alone.
(speaking in foreign language)
So the whole chapter keeps the camera on one thing,
which is the Ark of Covenant,
which is the lower right, the golden box here.
Now the Ark of Covenant was the mercy seat
of the throne of God, is overshadowed by cherubim,
and it is the throne of God, the place of his presence.
(speaking in foreign language)
So my question for you, what are cherubims?
What are cherubims?
Angels, yes.
(speaking in foreign language)
Yeah, angels.
And that's why in this series, I asked Pastor Ken,
what kind of item would represent the Ark of Covenant?
And he had a very good idea.
(speaking in foreign language)
And he said, "Use a feather."
Feather, you know why feather?
(speaking in foreign language)
Because the angelic wing, right?
Yeah.
And then, but, you know, cherubim,
the angels of the Bible are not the cute,
you know, hallmark little creatures.
They are very powerful beings,
and they guard and they carry the throne of God.
(speaking in foreign language)
In any case, the hero of the story of crossing Jordan
is not Joshua, it is not the people.
It is God himself going forward, going first.
God who sits on throne of the cherubim,
and he stepped into the impossible water
ahead of his people.
(speaking in foreign language)
This story tells you, at least first point,
is that you have to trust God every day.
(speaking in foreign language)
The first thing about this story
is to ask us for daily trust in God,
because God told the people,
"You have not passed this way before."
And you compare kind of the way
the Israelite crossed the Red Sea,
crossing Jordan River is a different situation.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then every day of our lives can be new,
you know, kind of like our story here.
Our headline can be, you know,
every one of our days is full of new situations
and uncertainties.
And the road, the new day is new,
but the story tells you the God who leads the road,
he leads your life, is the same God.
(speaking in foreign language)
Before they crossed the River Jordan,
God speaks through Moses.
Now there's no longer Moses.
Moses has passed away, right?
But Joshua leads the way and Joshua speaks.
Now you see the spoke person,
the mouthpiece had changed,
but the message of God had not.
Seasons of our lives can change.
You know, the paths can become uncertain and unfamiliar,
but God's word is forever settled,
forever settled in heaven.
And the authority is in his word,
not with the spoke person.
(speaking in foreign language)
- Now, of course we don't have the wooden box,
golden box in front of you, right?
We don't have a visible art today,
but we have the abiding presence of the enduring spirit.
When we trust in Jesus, the spirit lives in us.
And through the hills and valleys,
we can walk confidently in the fact that God is with you.
(speaking in foreign language)
- So the first question of Christian faith is not,
listen up, it's not whether we are strong enough.
It is not whether our faith is strong enough,
but it's whether God is faithful, strong enough.
(speaking in foreign language)
- And then God is the same every single day.
- That's the first point.
Second point here, the story tells you,
is that you have to wait on God every day
because his time is not our time.
(speaking in foreign language)
- Here's the wonder of the Hebrew original language.
You know, the verb stand or still
is used many times in this chapter.
(speaking in foreign language)
- As you can see in chapter three, verse eight,
it says to the people, to the priest,
you shall stand still in the river Jordan, in the water.
(speaking in foreign language)
- And then in verse 13, at the end,
the water coming down from the river above
shall stand in one heap.
(speaking in foreign language)
- And then verse 16, it says the waters,
when they step into the water and the water cut off,
the water coming down from above stood
and rose up in a heap very far away.
(speaking in foreign language)
- 16. - 16.
- And then finally, in verse 17, here on the screen,
the priest bearing the outer covenant,
they were carrying the outer covenant of the Lord,
stood firmly on dry ground in the midst of the river.
(speaking in foreign language)
- Now, you know, faith stands before,
you know, they step in by faith,
and faith is standing before you see the result, not after.
(speaking in foreign language)
- And then this is the faith of attention.
You know, you gotta stay back like 2,000 cupids
so that you can see the Ark of Covenant,
and you see the way, you know, they had never walked.
(speaking in foreign language)
- So you imagine, you know,
you're standing in the bank of the river,
and then the priest will step into the water,
and then you have to wait, wait for some time,
a long time, for the water to dry up.
(speaking in foreign language)
- And then if you rush forward,
you will miss what God is doing.
(speaking in foreign language)
- You see, God is less interested in what he does for you.
God is more interested in who you are becoming.
(speaking in foreign language)
- This is always how faith works in the Bible,
very long, slow waiting.
(speaking in foreign language)
- And then you think of Abraham,
he waited for 25 years for Isaac,
and then Joseph waited for years and years in Egypt
before he could save the family.
And then David was anointed to be a king,
but he spent years in persecutions.
(speaking in foreign language)
- You see, it's very interesting in the Bible,
the timing of God is rarely faster than our time.
It's usually slower, sometimes much slower,
yet the Lord is not slow about his promise.
(speaking in foreign language)
- You know, there's an old story about timing.
And then, you know, I wanna tell you this story today.
(speaking in foreign language)
- But because of AI, you know, I plucked a story into AI,
and then it produced a comic strip.
(speaking in foreign language)
- So this story goes, a young man who asked an angel,
how long is a million years to you?
(speaking in foreign language)
- And then the angel answer, well, about a minute.
- And then the young man asks another question,
how much is a million dollars to you?
(speaking in foreign language)
- Then the angel answer, well, it's like a penny.
- And then the young man asks again,
you would ask that question, then could you give me a penny?
(speaking in foreign language)
- And the angel reply, sure, in a minute.
- You get the point, right?
(speaking in foreign language)
- Now we cannot manipulate the clock of God,
we can only trust in it.
(speaking in foreign language)
- You see, we need to stand still and wait.
This is not to pressure God into acting,
it is follow the God who has already gone first.
(speaking in foreign language)
- You know, in the past 10 years at UV,
there were quite a few times I thought about,
you know, we thought about, the leaders thought about,
you know, maybe we should rent another room upstairs
or any room available, we want to expand our ministry.
(speaking in foreign language)
- Now you may also ask, why do we expand this time,
right, at this time?
(speaking in foreign language)
- You see, you look around the world,
we don't have the best economy ever.
(speaking in foreign language)
- But it's very interesting, very amazing
that God has opened the door for us this year.
The next unit, the next unit is open.
(speaking in foreign language)
- It may not be the best time, you know, humanly speaking.
- But we believe it is God's time.
(speaking in foreign language)
- As we think about this story, Joshua three to four,
maybe some questions we need to bring to ask ourselves.
The first one I want to ask you,
looking back your winding road, you know,
winding road for years,
where has God proved himself faithful
in the long season of waiting?
And how could remembering that will steady you today?
(speaking in foreign language)
- And the second question is, when God seems slow,
do you trust his timing?
Do you trust his timing and what is it right now
that you most need to entrust to God?
(speaking in foreign language)
- So remember for reflection,
the first question is looking back your winding road,
how has God proved himself faithful
in your season of waiting?
You know, how does this keep you going?
How does it keep you going?
And the second question is, when God seems so slow,
do you truly trust his timing?
What do you need to entrust to him right now?
(speaking in foreign language)
- Then question number three,
like the 12 stones, they cross the Jordan
and then they put the 12 stone as a memorial.
Now, what memorial of God's faithfulness
can I be leaving behind for the next generation?
(speaking in foreign language)
- Think about those questions this week.
- Okay, pick one feather on your way out.
(speaking in foreign language)
- Put it in our jar of anniversary.
- Let's all pray together.
(speaking in foreign language)
- Faithful God, you have carried us every step of the way
and it has never been late.
(speaking in foreign language)
- We pray that you teach us to trust in you each day
and to wait without forcing our way.
(speaking in foreign language)
- We believe that our Lord Christ Jesus
has gone ahead of us and hold us until we safely cross.
(speaking in foreign language)
- Thank you God, in Jesus' name we pray.
- Thank you, Jane.
(speaking in foreign language)
- Well, spend some time to get to know each other,
you know, have some time of fellowship
and remember to pick up some feather, okay?